There we go. We're
recording now. Hi everyone.
Welcome to the First Healthy,
R clinic of 2024.
Hope everyone had a really
nice festive season
and is looking forward
to the New Year.
Today we're going to be doing
our demo on venn diagrams,
which is a requested demo.
If anyone ever has any requests
of topics they'd
like us to cover,
I like to try and tailor
the clinics to things
that people actually
find useful and helpful
and might help their
day to day life.
We really appreciate requests.
Today you've got Neil with me
who is sharing his screen.
This is just IDE or
R studio interface
on Posit Cloud link
is in the chat,
it just shows us right now
it's the three panels.
But if you open up
the R markdown document that's
called one underscore venn
yes that one there we'll
see the four panels that
we're used to seeing.
The top left is the bottom
left is the console top right,
our environment where our
import imported
datasets will end up.
And then the bottom
right is where
all our scripts and
files are saved.
A few other tabs that
do different things,
but they are less
important Right now,
Neil has opened up the
R markdown document,
which is a place
where we can type
our code and also free text.
It's made up of a few things.
It's got the yaml
at the very top,
where is where you set
a bunch of metadata.
Things like the title
of the document,
the author, the date,
and lots of other different
customisable options.
Then we've got this
grayed out section
which is code chunk.
It's in the grade sections
that we type our R code.
And then in the white sections
where we can write free text.
Don't scroll right
to the bottom of
the document because I have
some answers just in
case we want to have
a check of those.
But can you make
the script quadrant a
bit bigger and
then maybe zoom in
slightly to make the
text slightly bigger?
Hey, is it okay?
Yeah, that looks good
If you scroll down,
if you just run the
data prep chunk that
I've made which has the packages
that we're going to use,
then just a few little bits.
Tidy verse is a package
that we frequently use,
really good for data
data wrangling.
You can see there all
the packages that it
loads in table Tidlist,
cetera, M. Then there
was a GG Ven package
that we're going to be
using for making our
ven diagrams today.
Janitor is just one
that I've used for this
clean names function,
which is just a
quick way to remove
special characters
and spaces from
your column headings to
make it a bit cleaner,
Upset R is something that
we're going to demonstrate
at the end when venn diagrams
get a bit complicated.
Excellent. Neil,
could you start off,
we've got a fresh dataset.
Don't know much about it.
Would you be able to open
up the dataset,
have a look at it,
and then maybe try
doing a few counts
on obesity, smoking, diabetes.
I should say quickly,
this is a dataset found online
from the tidy Tuesday database,
which is just made
it a really cool
location to get lots of
online datasets to practise
your coding skills.
This is just looking at
like a heart health
database kind of thing.
And I've just filtered
for 5,000 observations.
So yeah, sorry, rambling.
Now over to you if you can.
So what I always like to do is
just click on the
dataset and just have,
have a look at the visual
just to get a feel
for what's there.
So I can see we've got 26
columns here, 5,000 rows.
We've got patient ID,
some demographic information,
cholesterol measures of
blood pressure, heartbreak.
Family, history, smoking.
Okay. All kinds of information.
Stress level. Is that
like a self assessed?
General life stress measure.
Good question. I'm not sure.
Yeah, I guess it's
maybe self assessed.
I didn't quite learn about
how the variables were made.
I wonder what it means.
Okay, Someone's getting nine
out 10 hours sleep a day.
Look at them, what's
their stress level?
Stress level seven.
Okay. All right.
Right. Okay. So we've got all
kinds of information on it.
Looks like 5,000 individuals.
Yeah. And the reason
some of them are true
and false is because
I earlier in the script
changed it to true and false as
opposed to a binary one or zero.
Because that just makes
it much easier for
using the GG package.
But it's showing the
same kind of binary.
Yes. No content.
So we've got different
countries here,
so we could say, we could do
sort, sort that.
Okay. So it's quite evenly
distributed across
different countries.
So there's 200 and odd
from each country.
What else might
be interested in?
I'm going to go to that
stress level variable.
I want to see. I'm not sure
that it's quite evenly
distributed over
stress levels as well.
Yeah, what kind of
questions are we going
to be asking about
this data for this example?
These are all people that are,
it's information on their heart.
These are all people are
potentially at risk of
having a heart attack.
What we're going
to be looking at,
what we're going to
be looking at with
the Venn diagrams is
plotting the co morbidities
or other symptoms that these
people are experiencing.
For example, we're
going to be looking
at whether or not
they're smokers,
alcohol intake, et cetera.
Just to have a visualisation of
the co morbidities that
these people that all have
a history of heart disease have.
Should I make a plot, Sarah?
Yeah, I think plotting
your data before
you try and jump
into anything complicated
is always really important.
So maybe if you try
doing a bar plot,
if you do heart attack risk on
the x axis and then fill
the colour based on
diabetes and then
just have a check and
then do a geom_bar and have
a look at that risk.
Is that right, fill, fill
What it was called
diabetes or just any
of the comorbidity variables.
Perfect.
There we are. Now we've got
a really quick plot though.
It's zoom out slightly.
It's showing us the counts
of heart attack risk
is currently viewed as
a numeric variable,
which is why that is giving
us a continuous scale as
opposed to just one or zero.
Could you change that quickly?
Just make it a factor?
So am I allowed to do that?
Just in here at Yeah, you can.
I what Neil is doing
is changing the x variable to
a factor as opposed
to changing it in
the entire dataset because
we're just caring about it.
In this quick instance,
you can just put it into the
aesthetics bracket there.
When you scroll down,
you'll see that it's
changed x axis, it's Fct,
but you can see that
it's now 1.0 as
opposed to a continuous scale,
which wasn't correct because
even though it's
1.0 we know that
that's a two level
factor, not a number.
As now you can see that there's
over 3,000 people that are not
at risk of a heart attack,
under 2000 people
that are at risk.
And you can just
see how the spread
of those patients that have
diabetes split between
those two patients.
Yeah, just like you're saying,
counts and plots are really
important thing to do at
the very beginning
just so that you can
get to grips with your data,
you can see if there's
any abnormalities,
anything that you don't
expect, et cetera.
Now for the sake of time,
we will jump into the
actual Venn diagram part
of creating this diagram,
the bend diagram part
of the diagram demo.
I hadn't made many Ben diagrams
in R before this
request came in.
Did a bit of research
and there are lots
of ways to do it.
There's a package
called venndiagram,
which is quite popular to use,
but I found it quite
complicated and clunky and
you add to input a lot
of the numbers manually.
Instead, we're going to
be using this function,
ggvenn, which is from
the ggvenn package.
Which flows much more nicely
into a tidy verse work flow.
But just to let you
know that there's
other options out there.
What we're going to
start with now, Neil,
is as always going to start with
our dataset and pipe
into the function ggvenn.
Yes.
At its basic, all you
really need to do is
specify the columns that
you want to be included
in this V diagram.
If you do columns equals and
then do a combined like a C,
open brackets for this
one we're going to do,
you can do whatever
variables you're looking
at but why don't we do diabetes
and smoking and just to see how
those two variables
overlap and then run that.
The variables have to
be in quotations for
this yes
object just like that.
It's done all the
counting up for us.
It has to be in a logical format
which was why they were
all true and false before.
But that's just a really
quick and easy way
to get a really
simple venn diagram.
You can see it's got
the overlap and the two
numbers at the side.
When you say to be
a logical format,
does that mean that these
variables, diabetes,
these have to be true false
smoking To be true false,
it can't be 10 anything.
Yeah, it can't be 10,
even if it's viewed as a factor.
Logical format is what
you need to change it to.
But that's really simple.
If you scroll up slightly,
can I did it for us at
the very beginning here?
Slightly as logic,
it's really quick and
easy thing to do,
just as you would change things
to a factor or a number.
You can also change it to
a logical output there.
But yes, if you scroll
down again to the diagram,
this was a really quick
and easy way to do it.
But what I don't
like about it is
that the circles are equal.
Sizes might be a bit misleading.
It looks like the smokers
and those that have
diabetes is quite easy.
It doesn't look like
there's much overlap.
There's actually a
handy function in
this ggvenn package, not
function, argument
called auto underscore scale.
If you set auto
underscore scale to true,
that should help us out a bit.
There we go.
Now it's changed slightly.
It seems a lot more realistic
or visually at a glance,
you can see that
the smokers encapsulates
almost everyone
that is also diabetic.
I just think that's
a bit easier to see
the output as opposed to
the two even circles
that we had before.
You can change lots
of other things.
If you put F one on
the ggvenn function,
we can have a look at
some of the options,
but you can change
the colours and
the size of the font and
all of those things.
We're just opening up the
help document at the moment.
Just now, just to have a look at
all the things that we can
change in this venn diagram.
These are all default,
it's autoscale is false.
That's because the autoscaling
is only possible in
these simple venn diagrams
with two variables.
When it comes to more
complicated venn diagrams,
the mathematical
applicability of
having the correct
overlap of exact circles,
which is what we're plotting
here, gets too complicated.
You can't actually scale those.
I think that's why by
default it is false.
Why don't we have to go at
changing fill underscore colour.
Right now it's using
the blue and yellow.
But why don't we change
them to any colour?
We only need to give it two.
We dont need to give it three colours
because there are
three cos on the plot.
You need to give it two
and the middle colour,
because it's slightly
transparent,
like the alpha of 0.5 I
think it's just
overlapping those colours.
Brilliant. Now we've changed
the colours to purple and green.
You can change them
to, the opportunities
are pretty vast colour.
You can give colour
names or hex codes.
Try changing fill
Underscore alpha just so
we can have a look at
how the transparency works.
That middle overlap intersection
is just made up of a mix
of both of those colours.
But I think that's because
of the transparency.
If we make it 10
by default 0.51 it'll be opaque.
Yes. Yeah, that doesn't do
the overlap colour as much,
which I think the 0.5 default is
probably a good shots on.
The green has dominated,
taken president, if it's
zero with the puck.
All right, so colour at all.
So this is the overall.
Transparency of it. It's
not just the centre.
I guess that means the brain one
is being put over
the purple one.
Which is why when they
were fully colour blocked,
the green one was on top.
Makes sense.
Okay. Yes. That's just a
bit of a demonstration
that you can change
most things here.
You can change the text size,
you can change the colours,
you can change, you
can change almost anything
that you don't like about this.
And all you have to do
is add the argument
into your code junk.
Okay, let's try
three variables, okay?
Yeah, we've already pretty
much done that task there.
Skip that? No, no,
it's all right.
I was just trying to
formulate things in
my brain a bit more.
If you copy the code chunk
from task two into task four,
and then we can add
a third variable.
So that's the columns
she had like obesity
I think is the name
of the other column.
There we go. Just try
running that, right?
Yes. This is what I
was trying to mention
earlier that you can't
scale more than two.
The two venn diagram
looks quite nice because
you can scale it.
The circles are
proportional to the sample,
vaguely proportional
to the sample size.
But once you start
doing more than two,
it gets quite tricky.
We're going to have to take
out that autoscale argument.
We can't have
autoscale equals true.
This is the same with
the other functions
or the other packages that I was
looking at in how to
make venn diagrams.
The venn diagram package
also can't scale
on three or more usually.
What is this error?
Insufficient amount.
Okay. This is an
error that's come up.
It's quite nice to see errors.
It's basically telling
us that three is needed,
but only two is provided
in the manual scale.
This is in reference
to the colours.
We've given it two colours,
but now there's going
to be three circles.
We just have to give it
an extra colour. Perfect.
There we go.
Now we've got a Venn diagram of
our three comorbidities
and you can see
the overlap between
the intersection
between diabetes and smoking.
Smoking, obesity,
obesity, and diabetes,
and then also the
intersection of
all three in the middle there.
It's a bit trickier because you
can't scale the circles
to different sizes.
The overlap doesn't necessarily
match the size of the number
that it's giving you,
which I find a bit frustrating.
But when you're
using two variables,
it can be a nice way
to demonstrate three.
As long as you have
the numbers there,
it's not too complicated
to understand.
It starts getting really
hard with four variables,
which we can show just for
fun if you add a fourth
variable into the column.
If you add alcohol consumption,
alcohol underscore consumption.
And then you'll need to
add a fourth colour as
well. Any more colours.
Oh yeah, it gets a bit crazy.
I don't find this diagram
that useful any more.
Yes. Venn diagrams.
I think with two,
you can make some
really nice ones in
R. After that, they
get a bit tricky.
But now I'm going
to slightly pivot
the request to what
I would do if I
was trying to
visualise this data
in R. What I would do instead
was create an upset plot.
What does the
numbers that far out
that basically the question
is what does the
number represent?
Lost the chat. What does
the number represent
that appears
outside the diagram each time?
That is the patients that
don't fall into
these categories,
although they should
just be right.
Yeah, they're the ones that
are a false for everything.
30 patients are not
obese or smokers,
or diabetic or consume alcohol.
Yeah, it's a bit funny.
Theoretically here we
might want a circle.
Around the outside
of these are people
that have heart disease thing.
And then those 30 people
would fall into that circle,
but they don't have any
of the comorbidities
depending on what
you're actually
trying to visualise, right?
So this is not a
particularly useful diagram.
It could be, Yeah, I find,
I think upset plots would be
where I would jump to if I
was doing above three or maybe
even above two variables,
depending on the
type of journal or
publication or manuscript
you're trying to write.
If you scroll down
nesse lines of code
I've just written in advance,
I'm just creating
a new data frame
called Upset data from
our heart underscore
DF data frame.
I'm selecting the variables
I'm interested in.
I'm interested in the
column diabetes, obesity,
smoking, alcohol consumption,
and medication use.
You can imagine these five
variables in a Venn diagram.
There would be a lot of overlap.
It'd be very difficult to
work out what number
is representing,
but you might want
to have a diagram
that shows the patient.
You might want to know if
there's patients
that have lots of
these combilities or
if we're looking at
a dataset of people that
tend to just have one.
Yeah, there's just lots
of reasons why you
might want to have
a venn diagram style
diagram type information
in a different diagram.
One important thing to note is
that to use the upset plot,
you have to use this
function as.data.frame,
which turns it into a data
frame as opposed to a tibble,
which we use commonly.
In the tidyverse,
I think this is because upset,
the package that's coming
from is from five years ago,
which in Rs lifetime
is quite old, I guess.
It doesn't handle tibbles.
That's just something
to Oh yeah,
just there we can show
you without as a tibble.
And you can see the error
if that is helpful.
But it's just important
to note that sometimes
older packages
don't like tibbles,
which is a bit frustrating.
But yes, if you run that chunk,
the create the upset data.
Just the first part. Both parts.
Both lines we can do all.
We can talk through what the
second bit is doing as well.
Okay, there we go.
If you open upset data quickly,
just to have a look at so
everyone can see
what it looks like.
These are the columns
that we selected for.
Instead of true and false,
it's going back to
ones and zeros.
I did that in advance just
because it's a bit easier.
Upset needs ones and zeros as
opposed to trues and false.
That venn diagram needed,
that's what that was doing.
You'll notice the
column headings
are now back to having
capitals and spaces in them.
I'll explain why I did that.
We create an upset plot.
It's mostly just an
aesthetic thing.
If you go back into the
markdown document, Neil,
and create a new chunk and
we're we're going to
make an upset plot.
What you want to do is you're
using the function upset,
it's just upset
that would be upset
is the name of
the function that we're using
from the library upset?
Yeah, that's that, as you
can see in this helpful tab,
the things that it needs,
all you really need to
give it is the
dataset that we want.
If we start by doing
that upset data,
we can change some of
the aesthetics there.
If you run that, just
see what it makes.
There we go. Can you
use out slightly so we
can see it all at once?
This is what an upset
plot looks like.
I like to do order by
frequency because right
now it jumps around a lot.
It might actually be
easier if we add it in
the frequency order before
we talk through
what it's showing.
Yes, it's just order by
then, freq, in perfect.
And that just creates,
it's a bit easier to see because
the numbers are in
descending order.
Now, basically this is an
alternative to a Venn diagram.
The bars in the top
plot are counts
of how many individuals have
the combination described
using the lollipop things.
At the bottom, you'll see
that 440 people have obesity,
consume alcohol or
diabetic and smoke.
Then 434 take medication
for their heart,
consume alcohol,
diabetic and smoke and
so on This diagram,
you can see that most of
our patients have
multimorbidity.
If you can call these
co morbidities,
few patients have only
one or two combinations.
The reason I changed the
names of the columns early on
is that the bottom
half of the diagram,
you can see that it's
nicely formulated headings
as opposed to the
column headings that
would have had no
spaces and underscores.
Cool. I guess if
you go in the help tab
for the upset plot,
we can have a look at
some of the things that
we can customise with
this
number
of sets.
I guess that's if
you have lots of,
we only have five anyway.
But if you had more,
there might be some outliers
that are less informative.
So you might want to just reduce
that number, number
of intersects.
I think, yeah, that could be,
again, there might be some
outliers at the other end.
Is that 40 that we
have that like 40.
Anyway, you can change
the number of intersects
that you're interested in with
that order by frequency
is the main one that I do every
time I make one of these.
Because I think it's a bit more
informative to be able to see
that trend as opposed to
it being a bit more up
and down. Why don't we
We could change the minbar
label from intersection size.
We could change it
to whatever we want,
something like number
of patients or Yeah,
try number of patients.
Okay,
so label going
to call it number of
patients.
Let's change this.
Yeah, so let's change
that there so we can,
yeah, it doesn't have
to be intersection size,
which is the default.
You can change it to
whatever you want it to be.
Let's do one more and change
the colour of the main bars.
Let's do bar colour and
change it to whatever
colour we want.
When it comes to changing
all colours as a whole,
it's more of an
aesthetic thing as
opposed to trying to
convey information.
But it's sometimes
nice to have like
a theme of colours
that you use a lot.
Yeah, light blue is nice.
Now, those bars are blue.
Awesome. Yeah.
As you can see in the Help tab,
there's loads and those
are things that you
can do to change the point size,
line size, the numbers
that you see, the colours.
Yeah, I find upset plots
quite useful if you're
trying to convey diagram
like information.
But you've got too
many variables
but it gets a bit
too complicated.
Yeah.
Is it possible, the question,
is it possible to have
each colnability in
its own colour? Good question.
Let's see if we
can work that out.
If we have a look at
this is what I would do
or what we would do when
we're not sure. I've
never done that.
I would have a look
at these options.
I think it's set bar colour.
These are the sets. If we try
changing sets bar colours,
but create like a combined
and give them five
different colours,
see what happens, and
then we'll do fine
calls, give it a go.
I'm not sure if this will work.
Yeah. Okay. That's the bars.
Okay. That's those bars.
What other colours can we
sit if you find in topic?
If you search the word colour?
Sometimes I just like in
that one other search
box next to the,
although I think you'll have to
spell it the American way.
See what comes up?
A tribute colour?
It might be.
Yeah.
Oh, colour
of the intersection
points is that.
Yeah, I think it's
that. Give that one
it goes matrix colour.
Wanted.
So I'll just copy this.
Yeah, just use the same colours.
That is not what we wanted.
Oh, so that's just
looking for one colour.
Okay. Right, that's annoying.
It's just taking
the first colour
which is orange
and made them all.
I think that would
be would it be
the main bar plot if
you tried putting
the combined colour
list in there?
Is that what the
question was about
the currently blue
bars bar colour?
If I put this? I don't know.
Yeah, we can try it.
Yeah, I think that
that's for the main bars
that are going up and down.
I think, yeah, that technically
or whatever number it is.
I think ideally each
comorbidity where
the coloured bars
on the left hand side are,
each of the dots would
also have that colour,
just to make it easier to read.
But I don't think it's
going to take that.
It's taken orange
as the first colour
we've given it and just
coloured them all that way.
It looks like the answer is no.
A colour coming to go and
change all the colours.
A colour colour of
attribute histogram bins
or scetoblock points.
Okay. Yeah, actually that
sounds like it could be.
Try taking out the
matrix colour one.
And Agnes,
do you mean the ones that
are currently light blue?
That you would like to have
them different colours?
Yes. Yeah, I would have
wanted to see that
killed in different colours
depending on the
number of commodities.
But it seems like there
can only be one colour,
so That's okay.
Yeah. Yeah, I'm not sure if
you can change that one.
We'd have to give it
a colour for each,
567-89-1062
31 colours to
make it to manually set it,
unless we can give a palette.
I think I, yes,
I'm not quite sure, but
I can have a search.
And then before I upload
the code to this demo,
I can see if I can fix
it and then add that in.
But otherwise, does anyone
have any questions on
this content or
indeed any quick clinic
questions because
that ran on a bit.
Yes. I will share a link to
the previous videos on Github.
I'll do that right now. Right.
I'm going to stop the
recording and then we
can get any brief questions
if anyone has any.
And I'll share that
link just now.